Contact

8137606331 (Mobile) doclonghorn@msn.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ richardmortonbsnmha (LinkedIn) baptistjax.com (Company)

Top Skills

Healthcare Management Command Leadership

Languages

German

Certifications

Trauma Nursing Core Course Critical Care Registered Nurse (CCRN)

United States Army Certified Instructor

Lean Six Sigma Black Belt Training Advanced Cardiac Life Support Instructor

Publications

Development of a novel Global Trauma System Evaluation Tool and initial results of implementation in the Republic of South Sudan

Critical Care Transport in a Combat Environment: Building Tactical Trauma Transport Teams Before and During Deployment

Casualty Evacuation: An Innovative Role for Emergency Nurses

Richard Morton

System Director, Emergency Services Jacksonville, Florida Area

Summary

Over 30 years in healthcare with the last four in progressive, senior leadership in the largest non-profit North Florida Hospital System with additional responsibility as the System Lead for the organization's Veteran's Support Group and initiatives. 26 years of service in the United States Army with a diverse range of progressive executive, managerial, administrative, and clinical experiences with an emphasis on emergency, critical care, trauma, and evacuation medicine and nursing.

Goals:

Continuing to broaden my professional career as an executive clinical and administrative leader of healthcare with an emphasis on enhancing systems to maximize safe, effective, efficient, and fiscally and morally responsible care delivery

Specialties: American Association of Critical Care Nurses, CCRN 2007-Present

Emergency Nurses Association, TNCC 1996-Present Critical Care Nursing (US Army 8A) 1997-Present Emergency Nursing (US Army M5) 1996-Present

Leadership Philosophy: Meet me at the PASS! Great leaders create environments that are predictable, create direct and active accountability at all levels, sustain progress through evidence-based practice, embrace innovative approaches, and are rooted in standards...

Experience

Baptist Health 4 years 6 months

System Director, Emergency Services October 2018 - Present (1 year 9 months) Jacksonville, Florida

System Director for Adult and Blended Adult and Pediatric Emergency
Services geographically distributed across a four facility footprint in the largest
non-profit North Florida Hospital System. Directly supervise (4) Associate
Directors and Nurse Managers and (22) Supporting managers. Combined
responsibility for over 250 personnel and 130 emergency care beds servicing
over 170,000 visits annually with an annual operating budget of over \$20
million dollars. Additionally serve as the System Lead for the organization's
Veteran's Support Group and initiatives.

Director of Administrative Nursing and Emergency Services January 2016 - October 2018 (2 years 10 months) Jacksonville, Florida Area

Director of Administrative Nursing and Emergency Services for a 269 bed acute care hospital responsible for caring for over 50,000 emergency care patients annually with over 14,000 admissions and 67,000 out patient visits. Provide direct oversight for (6) associate directors of nursing (house supervisors) and (4) managers with a total of 140 staff. Responsible for all nursing administrative, patient flow and supervisory services, to include Nursing Supervision, facility bed management, staffing oversight, resuscitative support management, as well as all personnel, logistical, operational and fiscal requirements in the delivery of emergency care.

US Army
Chief Nursing Officer/Chief Clinical Operations
August 2014 - January 2016 (1 year 6 months)
Fort Benning, Georgia

Serves as the Deputy Commander/Chief Nurse and Chief of Clinical Operations for a 248 bed acute surgical care deployable hospital with 32 direct reporting senior directors/managers and oversight for 480 care delivery team members. Responsible to the Commander/Chief Executive Officer for oversight of Clinical Operations, training and readiness, preparatory operational exercise planning and execution, and direct support of all nursing and nursing support personnel. Collaborate with the Deputy Commander for Nursing/Chief Nursing Officer, Martin Army Community Hospital, as well as the 44th Medical Brigade and other commands to optimize clinical and operational nursing opportunities while maximizing fiscally responsible utilization of limited resources to ensure quality, patient centered care delivery for DoD personnel and their families.

212th Combat Support Hospital Assistant Chief Nurse Officer July 2013 - August 2014 (1 year 2 months)

Bruchmühlbach-Miesau, Germany

Serves as the Assistant Chief Nursing Officer for the United States Army's sole Combat Support Hospital in Europe. Responsible to the Commander and Chief Nurse for executive oversight of Clinical Operations, training and mission readiness, preparatory operational exercise planning and execution, and direct support of all nursing and nursing support personnel assigned to the 212th. Collaborate with Landstuhl Regional Medical Center and 21st TSC, as well as other DoD and NATO entities to optimize clinical and operational nursing opportunities while maximizing fiscally responsible utilization of limited resources to ensure quality, patient centered care delivery for DoD, NATO and non-NATO partners, personnel and their families in Europe.

Landstuhl Regional Medical Center
Director, Critical Care, Trauma, and Emergency Nursing
July 2012 - July 2013 (1 year 1 month)
Europe

Serves as Nursing Director/Chief for the Emergency and Critical Care departments at the primary Level I Trauma receiving and operational staging facility for all Department of Defense, NATO, and partner nation acutely wounded personnel serving in current combat operations.

Responsible for direct oversight of (4) managers and over 130 staff with an annual operating budget of over \$2 million dollars.

US Army Forces Command Clinical Operations Officer July 2011 - July 2012 (1 year 1 month) Fort Bragg, North Carolina

Serves as Clinical Operations Officer at US Army Forces Command, Surgeon's Office, Responsible for supporting the Command Surgeon in planning and integration of policy and combat casualty care delivery and preventative and restorative healthcare systems for over 750,000 US Army personnel worldwide. Collaborates with both DoD and international military and civilian medical partners to develop and implement solutions for delivering care in both combat operations and homeland security.

Tripler Army Medical Center
Executive Staff Officer, Department of Nursing
April 2011 - June 2011 (3 months)

Page 3 of 7

Staff Officer, supporting Regional Nurse Executive and Deputy Commander for Nursing of Pacific Regional Medical Command and Tripler Army Medical Center

USCENTCOM

Joint Forces Medical Evacuation Trauma Nurse Coordinator August 2010 - April 2011 (9 months)

US Army Medical Evacuation Lead Officer in a forward deployed, multicomponent, NATO Joint Theater Trauma System team comprised of Army, Air Force, Navy, and International subject matter experts in advanced tactical trauma management. Direct responsibility and oversight for the Secretary of Defense directed Central Command rotary wing (helicopter) aeromedical transport in support of Operation Enduring Freedom throughout the entire country of Afghanistan.

Tripler Army Medical Center 2 years 2 months

Executive Officer, Department of Nursing May 2009 - August 2010 (1 year 4 months)

Serves as the Executive Officer for the Department of Nursing. Manage and provide senior administrative oversight for over \$30,000,000 in hospital budget and contracting obligations. Serve as Senior Human Resources manager for over 1180 professional and paraprofessional nursing personnel. Serve as Senior Administrative Advisor to the Regional Nursing Executive/Deputy Commander for Nursing for the Pacific Regional Medical Command and Tripler Army Medical Center. Directly supervise (8) executive staff members in managing the operational activities of the Department.

Nurse Manager, Progressive Care Unit July 2008 - May 2009 (11 months)

Served as the Nurse Manager of an eight bed Progressive Care Unit with a staff of (30) military, civilian, and contract personnel, with Senior oversight responsibilities for \$685,000.00 and a personnel budget of approximately \$150,000.00 monthly.

United States Army School of Aviation Medicine Director, Enroute Care Branch July 2006 - July 2008 (2 years 1 month)

Serves as the Senior Director and advisor to the Dean, Unites States Army School of Aviaition Medicine, for all rotary wing aeromedical transport (Flight Medic (68WF) and enroute care personnel (MD, RN, LPN, Flight Medic)) training for the United States Army in a Tri-service, Department of Defense program training over 300 students annually, served as a subject matter expert in rotary wing transport on the United States Transportation Command (USTRANSCOM) Global Patient Movement Joint Advisory Board and the United States Army Medical Material Agency rotary wing aeromedical transport equipment review team.

101st Airborne Division/772nd Forward Surgical Team Director of Nursing June 2004 - June 2006 (2 years 1 month)

Fort Campbell, KY/Deployed: Iraq

Supervise and manage over \$1,000,000 dollars in equipment, and oversee nursing care delivery by (20) personnel in a mobile surgical and emergency care team that provides crucial support to deployed DoD personnel and civilians in global combat operations.

Baylor University
MHA Student/Administrative Resident
June 2002 - June 2004 (2 years 1 month)

Graduate Student/Admnistrative Resident in the Department of Defense's Joint Service, Premiere Baylor University Healthcare Administration Program

Medical Task Force Eagle Base Camp, Bosnia Information Management Officer/ Clinical Education Coordinator/ Critical Care Nurse August 2001 - January 2002 (6 months)

Served as the Information Management Officer (S-6), Clinical Education and Trauma Training Coordinator, and a Senior Staff Critical Care Nurse for a forward deployed Combat Support Hospital

28th Combat Support Hospital
Critical Care Staff Nurse
September 2000 - August 2001 (1 year)

Served as a Critical Care Staff Nurse in one of the Department of Defense's premier, multifunctional, Combat Support Hospitals

31st Combat Support Hospital Nurse Manager/Critical Care Staff Nurse December 1999 - July 2000 (8 months) Supervised and managed 20 personnel as Nurse Manager for a 12 bed, mobile Intensive Care Unit in a US Army Combat Support Hospital

William Beaumont Army Medical Center Critical Care Staff Nurse December 1997 - July 2000 (2 years 8 months)

Served as a Critical Care Staff Nurse and Trauma and Burn Training Coordinator for a Level Two Trauma Center. Provided emergency filler support for Brooke Army Medical Center's Burn Intensive Care Unit during critical infectious disease crisis.

Eisenhower Army Medical Center
Emergency Department Staff Nurse
August 1995 - August 1997 (2 years 1 month)
Staff Nurse in a 20 bed Level III Emergency Department

Veteran's Adminstration Hospital, Augusta, Georgia Licensed Practical Nurse, Neuro-Surgical Unit January 1992 - January 1995 (3 years 1 month)

Served as a Staff Nurse on a large, multi-functional neurosurgical unit managing advanced spinal cord injury and post-operative neurosurgical care

Johnson City Medical Center Licensed Practical Nurse January 1991 - January 1992 (1 year 1 month) Neurosurgical unit staff nurse

Walter Reed Army Medical Center, Cardiac/Cardiothoracic Intensive Care

Licensed Practical Nurse January 1989 - January 1991 (2 years 1 month)

Licensed Practical Nurse in a Cardiac/Cardiothroacic Intensive Care Unit providing advanced clinical support to (1-2) critical care patients

Education

Jacksonville University

Doctor of Nursing Practice, Executive Leadership · (2017 - 2021)

Baylor University

MHA, Healthcare Administration · (2002 - 2004)

Medical College of Georgia at Augusta University BSN, Nursing · (1993 - 1995)

Augusta State University
Pre-Nursing (BSN), Pre-nursing · (1992 - 1993)

Maryville, High School Diploma · (1982 - 1986)